CATRIONA SILVEY

c.silvey@ucl.ac.uk

www.homepages.ucl.ac.uk/~ucjuca2

Division of Psychology and Language Sciences, University College London Room 302, Chandler House, Wakefield Street, London WC1N 1PF

SUMMARY

My research focuses on the acquisition and evolution of word meanings. My skills include designing and running linguistically motivated experiments with human participants and applying novel analysis methods to complex data, with additional experience in project and people management.

EMPLOYMENT

University College London, UK

British Academy Postdoctoral Fellow
(maternity leave from June-Dec 2020)

University of Chicago, USA

Postdoctoral Scholar, Language Development Project

2014-2017

EDUCATION

University of Edinburgh, UK

PhD Linguistics 2011–2014

- The communicative emergence and cultural evolution of word meanings
- Supervisors: Kenny Smith and Simon Kirby

University of Edinburgh, UK

MSc Evolution of Language & Cognition

2010-2011

University of Chicago, USA

MA Humanities 2006–2007

University of Cambridge, UK

BA English (1st class honours)

2003-2006

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- Silvey, C., Demir-Lira, Ö. E., Goldin-Meadow, S. & Raudenbush, S. (in press). Effects of time-varying parent input on child language outcomes differ for vocabulary and syntax. *Psychological Science*.
- Silvey, C., Kirby, S., and Smith, K. (2019). Communication increases category structure and alignment only when combined with cultural transmission. *Journal of Memory and Language*, 109, 104051. doi: 10.1016/j.jml.2019.104051 Data and analysis scripts
- Silvey, C., Kirby, S., & Smith, K. (2015). Word meanings evolve to selectively preserve distinctions on salient dimensions. *Cognitive Science*, *39*(1), 212-226.

OTHER ARTICLES

- Silvey, C. (2016). Speaking Our Minds: Why human communication is different, and how language evolved to make it special, by Thom Scott-Phillips. *Journal of Language Evolution*, *1*(1), 88-90.
- Silvey, C. (2014). Functions of language: Communication is basic, categorisation is derived. Invited response to Dialog, *IEEE CIS Newsletter on Autonomous Mental Development*, 11(1), 8-9.
- Silvey, C., & Smith, K. (2014). Mechanisms of cultural transmission and language learning. In P. J. Brooks & V. Kempe (Eds.), *Encyclopaedia of Language Development*. Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE Publications.

SELECTED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- Silvey, C., Gentner, D., Richland, L. E., & Goldin-Meadow, S. (2017). Children's spontaneous comparisons from 26 to 58 months predict performance in verbal and non-verbal analogy tests in 6th grade. In G.Gunzelmann, A. Howes, T. Tenbrink, & E. Davelaar (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 39th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society*, 1072-1077. Austin, TX: Cognitive Science Society.
- Silvey, C., Demir-Lira, Ö. E., & Goldin-Meadow, S. (2016). Children's status and growth in word types at 20 months predicts age of onset of complex syntax. Talk at Boston University Conference on Language Development, 41.
- Silvey, C., & Christodoulopoulos, C. (2016). Children's production of determiners: A test case for innate syntactic categories. In S. G. Roberts, C. Cuskley, L. McCrohon, L. Barceló-Coblijn, O. Feher, & T. Verhoef (Eds.), *The Evolution of Language: Proceedings of the 11th International Conference (EVOLANG11)*. doi:10.17617/2.2248195.
- Silvey, C., Flaherty, M., Goldin-Meadow, S., Kirby, S., & Smith, K. (2016). Communication without a language model inhibits the emergence of systematic structure. In S. G. Roberts, C. Cuskley, L. McCrohon, L. Barceló-Coblijn, O. Feher, & T. Verhoef (Eds.), *The Evolution of Language: Proceedings of the 11th International Conference (EVOLANG11)*. doi:10.17617/2.2248195.
- Silvey, C. (2014). The origins of word meaning. In E. A. Cartmill, S. Roberts, H. Lyn, & H. Cornish (Eds.), *The Evolution of Language: Proceedings of the 10th International Conference (EVOLANG10)*. Singapore: World Scientific.
- Silvey, C., Kirby, S., & Smith, K. (2013). Communication leads to the emergence of sub-optimal category structures. In M. Knauff, M. Pauen, N. Sebanz, & I. Wachsmuth (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 35th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society*, 1312-1317. Austin, TX: Cognitive Science Society.

INVITED TALKS

- Silvey, C. (2018). Investigating the origin of relational word meanings. Invited talk at UCL Language & Cognition seminar, Nov 2018.
- Silvey, C. (2017). Children's specific comparisons and later analogical skill. Invited talk at Northwestern University, May 2017.
- Silvey, C. (2015). Linguistic categories are shaped by communication and cultural transmission. Invited talk at University of Wisconsin Madison, February 2015.

GRANTS AND AWARDS

- British Academy Postdoctoral Fellowship, 2017
- Arts and Humanities Research Council travel grant, 2014
- Grindley Grant from Experimental Psychology Society, 2013
- Carnegie-Cameron Postgraduate Bursary, 2010–2011
- Catherine Ham Memorial Award for Excellence, 2007
- Gaylord Donnelley Exchange Scholarship, 2006–2007
- Bishop Green Cup, Foundation Scholarship, 2006

TEACHING

University College London, UK

Lecturer/Tutor - Web Programming

2019

• Taught module on using HTML, Javascript, and PHP to design and build online experiments

Module Leader 2018

• Coordinated Practical Research Skills module for MSci students

Workshop Leader 2018

• Designed and led workshop on data visualisation in R

University of Chicago, USA

Supervisor 2016-2017

- Supervised PhD student's silent gesture project
- Trained undergraduate RA in coding children's spontaneous comparisons
- Supervised high school summer project on part-of-speech tagging

Lecturer/Tutor 2015

• Undergraduate introduction to language evolution and language development

University of Edinburgh, UK

Supervisor **2012, 2013**

• Supervised two MSc projects

• Provided technical and experimental design advice to MSc cohort

Tutor 2012–2013

Introduction to Statistics and Experimental Design

Guest Lecturer 2013

• Linguistics and English Language 1 (first year undergraduate course). Talk summarising research, 'Word meanings and categories'

NON-ACADEMIC Public Library of Science (PLOS), Cambridge, UK

EMPLOYMENT

Editorial Freelancer

2011-2014

• Freelance editorial work for former full-time employer.

Publications Assistant/Publications Manager

2008-2010

• Scientific journal publishing. Managed workload of team split between Cambridge and San Francisco; line managed UK team members; managed projects.

TECHNICAL

SKILLS

Data Analysis:

• Mixed-effects models, hierarchical linear modelling, causal inference methods, Bayesian analysis and Bayes factors, SPSS, R, ELAN video annotation, corpus analysis, part-of-speech tagging, dependency parser training and evaluation, gesture transcription & analysis

Computer Programming:

• Python (including PsychoPy), R, HTML, PHP, SQL, LaTeX, E-Prime

Professional

SERVICE

Referee Service

- PNAS, Cognition, Linguistics, Open Mind, Journal of Language Evolution
- CogSci (since 2016); Evolang (since 2014)

Conference Service

Organising committee for Linguistics and English Language Postgraduate Conference, University of Edinburgh, May 2013

Public Engagement

- Co-organiser for Language Evolves, workshop and short story competition aiming to introduce science fiction authors to language evolution research, 2020
- Online expert for Christmas Lectures Zone, taking part in live chats with schools and answering questions from the public, January 2018
- Panellist on Universal Translator tropes in science fiction at WisCon science fiction & fantasy convention, Madison, USA